Well, as Alexander Graham Bell famously said
حسناً، كما ألاسكندر غراهام بيل في قولته المشهورة
on his first successful telephone call,
في أول مكالمة تلفونية ناجحة،
"Hello, is that Domino's Pizza?"
" مرحبا، هل هذا دومينوس بيتزا؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I just really want to thank you very much.
أود حقيقة أن أشكركم جداً.
As another famous man, Jerry Garcia, said,
وكما قال رجل مشهور آخر، جيري غارسيا،
"What a strange, long trip."
"يا لغرابة وطول الرحلة."
And he should have said,
وكان يتوجب عليه القول،
"What a strange, long trip it's about to become."
"يالغرابة، وطول رحلة علي وشك ان تتحقق ."
At this very moment, you are viewing my upper half.
في هذه اللحظة، انتم تشاهدون نصفي الاعلي.
My lower half is appearing at a different conference
نصفي الاسفل يظهر في مؤتمر آخر --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
in a different country.
في بلد آخر.
You can, it turns out, be in two places at once.
يمكنك، كما تبين، ان تكون في مكانين في أن واحد.
But still, I'm sorry I can't be with you in person.
ولكن يظل، اعتذر عن عدم تمكني ان اكون معكم شخصياً.
I'll explain at another time.
ساوضح في وقت اخر.
And though I'm a rock star,
وبالرغم من انني نجم موسيقي،
I just want to assure you that none of my wishes will include a hot tub.
اود ان اوكد لكم ان ايٌ من امنياتي لن تشمل حوض أستحمام ساخن.
But what really turns me on about technology
لكن حقيقة ما يجذبني نحو التكنولوجيا
is not just the ability to get more songs on MP3 players.
ليست مجرد القدرة على الحصول على المزيد من الأغاني على مشغلات الموسيقي.
The revolution -- this revolution -- is much bigger than that.
الثورة -- هذه الثورة -- اكبر بكثير من ذلك.
I hope, I believe.
آمل، اعتقد.
What turns me on about the digital age,
ما يشّدني حول العصر الرقمي،
what excites me personally,
ما يُثيرني شخصياً،
is that you have closed the gap between dreaming and doing.
هو انكم سددتم الفراغ بين الحلم وتحقيقه.
You see, it used to be that if you wanted to make a record of a song,
كما ترون، كانت العادة إذا رغبت بتسجيل أغنية،
you needed a studio and a producer.
تحتاج استديو و منتج.
Now, you need a laptop.
ألان، تحتاج إلي حاسوب شخصي.
If you wanted to make a film, you needed a mass of equipment
إذا اردت ان تصنع فيلماً ، تحتاج كمية من المعدات
and a Hollywood budget.
وميزانية هوليوود.
Now, you need a camera that fits in your palm,
ألان، تحتاج إلي كاميرا تسع راحة يدك
and a couple of bucks for a blank DVD.
وبضعة دولارات لاقراص مدمجة فارغة.
Imagination has been decoupled from the old constraints.
الخيال قد انفصل عن القيود القديمة.
And that really, really excites me.
وهذا حقاً، حقاً يُثيرُني
I'm excited when I glimpse that kind of thinking writ large.
انا متحمس عندما ألمح هذا النوع من التفكير في أوضح صوره.
What I would like to see is idealism decoupled from all constraints.
ما أود أن أراه هو إنفصال المثالية عن كل القيود.
Political, economic, psychological, whatever.
سياسياً، إقتصادياً، نفسياً، أياً كانت.
The geopolitical world has got a lot to learn from the digital world.
الجغرافيا السياسية لديها الكثير لتتعلمه من العالم الرقمي.
From the ease with which you swept away obstacles
من السهولة التي أزالت العقبات
that no one knew could even be budged.
والتي لا أحد يعلم بانها قد تتغير.
And that's actually what I'd like to talk about today.
وهذاحقيقةً ما أود التحدث عنه اليوم.
First, though, I should probably explain why, and how,
أولاً، رغم ذلك, ينبغي علي تفسير لماذا، وكيف،
I got to this place.
وصلت إلي هذا المكان.
It's a journey that started 20 years ago.
إنها رحلة بدأت قبل 20 عاماً.
You may remember that song, "We Are the World,"
ربما تذكرون تلك الاغنية، "نحن العالم"،
or, "Do They Know It's Christmas?"
أو، "هل يعلمون أنه عيد الميلاد؟"
Band Aid, Live Aid.
باند ايد، لايف ايد.
Another very tall, grizzled rock star, my friend Sir Bob Geldof,
شخص اخر طويل جداً، نجم الروك الاشهب، صديقي سير بوب غيلدوف،
issued a challenge to "feed the world."
أصدر التحدي "اطعم العالم".
It was a great moment, and it utterly changed my life.
لقد كانت لحظة عظيمة، وقد غيرت حياتي تماماً.
That summer, my wife, Ali, and myself went to Ethiopia.
في ذلك الصيف، زوجتي آلي، وشخصي ذهبنا إلي أثيوبيا.
We went on the quiet to see for ourselves what was going on.
ذهبنا بصمت لنري بانفسنا ما يحدث.
We lived in Ethiopia for a month, working at an orphanage.
عشنا في أثيوبيا لمدة شهر ، نعمل في مركز للأيتام.
The children had a name for me.
ألاطفال لديهم أسم لي.
They called me, "The girl with the beard."
يدعونني، " الفتاة صاحبة اللحية"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Don't ask.
لا تسأل.
Anyway, we found Africa to be a magical place.
علي أي حال، إكتشفنا ان أفريقيا مكان ساحر.
Big skies, big hearts, big, shining continent.
سماوات كبيرة، قلوب كبيرة، وقارة كبيرة وساطعة.
Beautiful, royal people.
أُناس جميلين و مخلصين.
Anybody who ever gave anything to Africa got a lot more back.
أي شخص أعطي شئ لافريقيا أخذ أشياء أكثر في المقابل.
Ethiopia didn't just blow my mind; it opened my mind.
أثيوبيا لم تكن فقط أخاذة للعقل: ولكن فتحت آفاقي.
Anyway, on our last day at this orphanage
علي أي حال، في اخر يوم في الملجأ
a man handed me his baby and said,
ناولني رجل طفله وقال،
"Would you take my son with you?"
"هلا أخذت ابني معك؟"
He knew, in Ireland, that his son would live,
كان يعلم، أنه في أيرلند، سيعيش أبنه،
and that in Ethiopia, his son would die.
ولكن في أثيوبيا، ابنه سيموت.
It was the middle of that awful famine.
كان ذلك في منتصف المجاعة الفظيعة.
Well, I turned him down.
حسناً، أنا رفضت عرضه.
And it was a funny kind of sick feeling, but I turned him down.
وكان ذلك أحساس غريب بالغثيان، ولكني رفضته.
And it's a feeling I can't ever quite forget.
ولكنه إحساس لا يمكنني نسيانه تماماً.
And in that moment, I started this journey.
وفي تلك الحظات، بدأت هذه الرحلة.
In that moment, I became the worst thing of all:
في تلك اللحظة، صرت اسوأ شي علي إلإطلاق:
I became a rock star with a cause. (Laughter)
أصبحت نجم روك مع قضية.
Except this isn't the cause, is it?
ما عدا أنه هذه ليست القضية، اليس كذلك؟
Six-and-a-half thousand Africans dying every single day from AIDS --
ستة الاف ونصف أفريقي يموتون كل يوم من الايدز --
a preventable, treatable disease --
مرض يمكن الوقاية منه، العلاج منه --
for lack of drugs we can get in any pharmacy.
لنقص في عقاقير يكمننا الحصول عليها من اي صيدلية.
That's not a cause. That's an emergency.
تلك ليست قضية. تلك حالة طارئة.
11 million AIDS orphans in Africa,
11 مليون يتيم لمرض الايدز في أفريقيا،
20 million by the end of the decade.
20 مليون بنهاية هذا العقد.
That's not a cause. That's an emergency.
تلك ليست قضية. تلك حالة طارئة.
Today, every day, 9,000 more Africans
اليوم، وكل يوم، 9,000 أفريقي إضافيين
will catch HIV because of stigmatization and lack of education.
سيصابون بمرض الايدز وذلك بسبب وصمة العار وقلة التعليم.
That's not a cause. That's an emergency.
تلك ليست قضية. تلك حالة طارئة.
So what we're talking about here is human rights.
إذاً ما نتحدث عنه هو حقوق الانسان.
The right to live like a human.
الحق في العيش مثل البشر.
The right to live, period.
الحق في الحياة، على الإطلاق.
And what we're facing in Africa is
وما نواجهه في افريقيا هو
an unprecedented threat to human dignity and equality.
تهديد غير مسبوق للكرامة الانسانية و المساواة.
The next thing I'd like to be clear about is what this problem is,
الشئ التالي الذي احب ان أكون واضحاً حوله ما تمثله هذه المشكلة،
and what this problem isn't.
وما لا تمثله المشكلة.
Because this is not all about charity.
لان هذا ليس عن الجمعيات الخيرية فقط.
This is about justice. Really.
هذا عن العدالة. حقيقة.
This is not about charity. This is about justice.
هذا ليس عن الجمعيات الخيرية. هذا عن العدالة.
That's right.
هذا صحيح.
And that's too bad, because we're very good at charity.
وهذا سئ جداً، لاننا جيدون جداً في الاعمال الخيرية.
Americans, like Irish people, are good at it.
الشعب الامريكي، مثل الشعب الايرلندي، يحبون ذلك.
Even the poorest neighborhoods give more than they can afford.
وحتي أفقر الاحياء تعطي أكثر مما تتحمل.
We like to give, and we give a lot.
نحن نحب العطاء، ونحن نعطي كثيراً.
Look at the response to the tsunami -- it's inspiring.
أُنظر للإستجابة لكارثة تسونامي، أنها ملهمة.
But justice is a tougher standard than charity.
ولكن معيار العدالة أكثر صرامة من الاعمال الخيرية.
You see, Africa makes a fool of our idea of justice.
أترون، أفريقيا تسخر من فكرتنا عن العدالة.
It makes a farce of our idea of equality.
وتعمل مهزلة من فكرتنا حول المساواة.
It mocks our pieties. It doubts our concern.
انها تسخر من معتقداتنا، تتشكك في إهتماماتنا.
It questions our commitment.
تتسائل عن التزاماتنا.
Because there is no way we can look at what's happening in Africa,
لأنه لامجال بالنظر لما يحدث في أفريقيا،
and if we're honest,
وإذا كنا صادقين،
conclude that it would ever be allowed to happen anywhere else.
نخلص الي انه لن يسمح مطلقاً بحدوث ذلك في مكان آخر.
As you heard in the film, anywhere else, not here.
كما سمعتم في الفيلم، اي مكان اخر، ليس هنا.
Not here, not in America, not in Europe.
ليس هنا، ليس في امريكا، ليس في اوروبا.
In fact, a head of state that you're all familiar with
في الواقع، رئيس دولة جمعيكم يعرفه
admitted this to me. And it's really true.
أعترف لي بذلك. وهي فعلاً حقيقة.
There is no chance this kind of hemorrhaging of human life
لا يوجد أي احتمال هذا النوع من النزف في الأرواح البشرية
would be accepted anywhere else other than Africa.
ان يكون مقبولاً في اي مكان اخر عدا أفريقيا.
Africa is a continent in flames.
أفريقيا قارة في لهيب.
And deep down, if we really accepted that Africans were equal to us,
وفي قرارة النفس، إذا قبلنا حقيقة ان الافارقة هم متساوون معنا،
we would all do more to put the fire out.
ينبغي علينا عمل المزيد لإخماد الحريق
We're standing around with watering cans,
ونحن نقف حاملين صفائح ماء ،
when what we really need is the fire brigade.
في حين مانحتاجه فرقة إطفاء.
You see, it's not as dramatic as the tsunami.
تعلمون، إنها ليست درامية كأحداث تسونامي.
It's crazy, really, when you think about it.
إنه جنون حقاً، إذا فكرتم في الامر.
Does stuff have to look like an action movie these days
هل يجب ان تبدو الاشياء كأفلام العُنف هذه ألايام
to exist in the front of our brain?
حتي تتجلي أمام عقولنا؟
The slow extinguishing of countless lives
ألبُطء لانقاذ ارواح لا تُحصي
is just not dramatic enough, it would appear.
ليس درامياً بالقدر الكافي، كما يجب.
Catastrophes that we can avert
الكوارث التي يمكن إجتنابها
are not as interesting as ones we could avert.
ليست مثيرة للإهتمام والتي كنا قادرين علي تفاديها.
Funny, that.
مضحك، هذا.
Anyway, I believe that that kind of thinking
باي حال، أعتقد بان هذا النوع من التفكير
offends the intellectual rigor in this room.
أساء إلي حاذقي الفكر في هذه الغرفة
Six-and-a-half thousand people dying a day in Africa may be Africa's crisis,
ستة ألاف ونصف شخص يموتون في أفريقيا يوميا ربما أزمات أفريقيا،
but the fact that it's not on the nightly news,
ولكن الحقيقة انها ليست في الاخبار المسائية،
that we in Europe, or you in America,
انه نحن في أوروبا، أو في أمريكا،
are not treating it like an emergency --
لا تتعامل معها مثل حالة طارئة --
I want to argue with you tonight that that's our crisis.
أود ان أتجادل معكم الليلة أن هذه أزمتنا.
I want to argue that though Africa is not the front line in the war against terror,
أود الجدال انه بالرغم من ان افريقيا ليست على خط المواجهة في الحرب ضد الارهاب
it could be soon.
يمكن ان يكون قريباً.
Every week, religious extremists take another African village.
كل أسبوع، المتطرفين الدينين يأخذون قرية أفريقية اخري.
They're attempting to bring order to chaos.
انهم يحاولون اعادة النظام الى الفوضى.
Well, why aren't we?
حسناً، لماذا ليس نحن؟
Poverty breeds despair. We know this.
الفقر يولد اليأس. نحن نعرف ذلك.
Despair breeds violence. We know this.
اليأس يولد العنف. نحن نعرف ذلك.
In turbulent times, isn't it cheaper, and smarter,
في الأوقات العصيبة، اليس من السُهولة، والذكاء،
to make friends out of potential enemies
كسب صداقات من أعداء محتملين
than to defend yourself against them later?
بدلاً من الدفاع عن نفسك في مواجهتهم لاحقاً؟
"The war against terror is bound up in the war against poverty."
الحرب علي إلإرهاب مرتبط بالحرب على الفقر.
And I didn't say that. Colin Powell said that.
لم أقل أنا ذلك، كولين باول قالها.
Now when the military are telling us that this is a war
الان عندما يحدثنا العساكر عن ان هذه حرب
that cannot be won by military might alone,
لا يمكن الفوز فيها بالقوة العسكرية فقط،
maybe we should listen.
ربما يجب أن نُصغي.
There's an opportunity here, and it's real.
هنالك سانحة ما هنا، وهي حقيقية.
It's not spin. It's not wishful thinking.
إنها ليست مناورة. وليست فكرة أمنيات.
The problems facing the developing world
المشاكل التي تواجه العالم النامي
afford us in the developed world
تمنحنا نحن في العالم المتقدم
a chance to re-describe ourselves to the world.
فرصة لإعادة وصف انفسنا للعالم.
We will not only transform other people's lives,
نحن لن نغير حياة أشخاص اخرين فقط،
but we will also transform the way those other lives see us.
ولكن أيضاً سنغير الطريقة التي يرانا بها هولاء الاخرين
And that might be smart in these nervous, dangerous times.
وذلك يمكن ان يكون من الذكاء في اوقات العصيبة، الخطيرة.
Don't you think that on a purely commercial level,
ألا تعتقدون ذلك في مستوى تجاري بحت،
that anti-retroviral drugs are great advertisements
أن العقاقير المضادة للفيروسات هي اعلانات كبيرة
for Western ingenuity and technology?
للبراعة والتكنلوجيا الغربية؟
Doesn't compassion look well on us?
الا يبدو التعاطف جيداً معنا؟
And let's cut the crap for a second.
ودعونا نترك المهاترات للحظة.
In certain quarters of the world, brand EU, brand USA,
في أصقاع معينة من العالم، العلامة التجارية للاتحاد الاوروبي، العلامة التجارية للولايات المتحدة الامريكية،
is not at its shiniest.
ليست في كامل إشراقها.
The neon sign is fizzing and cracking.
اللوحة المضيئة تخفو و تتشقق.
Someone's put a brick through the window.
شخص ما رمى حجراً عبر النافذة.
The regional branch managers are getting nervous.
مسئولو الفروع إلاقليمية يزدادون عصبية.
Never before have we in the west been so scrutinized.
لم يحدث لنا من قبل نحن في الغرب هذا التمحيص.
Our values: do we have any?
قيمنا: هل لدينا منها؟
Our credibility?
مصداقيتنا؟
These things are under attack around the world.
هذه الاشياء تتعرض لهجوم حول العالم.
Brand USA could use some polishing.
العلامة التجارية الامريكية يمكن ان تستخدم بعض التلميع.
And I say that as a fan, you know?
وانا اقول ذلك كمعجب، تعلمون؟
As a person who buys the products.
باعتباري شخص يشتري المنتجات.
But think about it.
ولكن فكر بذلك.
More anti-retrovirals make sense.
مزيد من مضادات الفيروسات تبدو معقولة.
But that's just the easy part, or ought to be.
لكن هذا ليس سوى الجزء السهل ، أو ينبغي أن يكون.
But equality for Africa --
ولكن المساواة لافريقيا --
that's a big, expensive idea.
تلك فكرة كبيرة، ومكلفة.
You see, the scale of the suffering numbs us into a kind of indifference.
اتلاحظون، حجم المعاناة يخّدرنا إلي نوع من اللامبالاة.
What on earth can we all do about this?
ماذا يمكننا جميعاً فعله حول هذا؟
Well, much more than we think.
حسناً، أكثر بكثير مما نعتقد.
We can't fix every problem, but the ones we can,
نحن لا يمكننا اصلاح اي مشكلة، ولكن التي نستطيع،
I want to argue, we must.
أود القول، يجب علينا فعلها.
And because we can, we must.
ولاننا نستطيع، يجب علينا ذلك.
This is the straight truth, the righteous truth.
هذه هي الحقيقة المباشرة، الحقيقة الصالحة.
It is not a theory.
أنها ليست نظرية.
The fact is that ours is the first generation
والحقيقة هي اننا أول الاجيال
that can look disease and extreme poverty in the eye,
التى يمكن ان ان تري الامراض وشدة الفقر بالعين،
look across the ocean to Africa, and say this, and mean it:
انظر عبر المحيط الي أفريقيا، وقل ذلك، واعني ما تقول.
we do not have to stand for this.
لا يتوجب علينا التصدي لذلك.
A whole continent written off -- we do not have to stand for this.
قارة كاملة تُمْسح -- لا يتوجب علينا التصدي لذلك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And let me say this without a trace of irony --
ودعوني أقول هذا من غير اثر للسخرية --
before I back it up to a bunch of ex-hippies.
قبل أن أدعمه بحفنة من الروحانيين السابقين.
Forget the '60s. We can change the world.
تجاهلوا فترة الستينات، يمكننا تغيير العالم.
I can't; you can't, as individuals; but we can change the world.
أنا لا أستطيع، انت لا تستطيع، كأفراد، ولكن نحن نستطيع تغيير العالم.
I really believe that, the people in this room.
أنا أعتقد حقيقي في ذلك، الاشخاص في هذه القاعة .
Look at the Gates Foundation.
أنظر إلي مؤسسة غيتس.
They've done incredible stuff, unbelievable stuff.
لقد فعلوا أشياء مُذهلة، أشياء لا تُصدق.
But working together, we can actually change the world.
ولكن بالعمل سوياً، يمكننا فعلياً تغيير العالم.
We can turn the inevitable outcomes,
يمكننا أن نغير النتائج التي لا مفر منها
and transform the quality of life for millions of lives
وتحويل نوعية حياة ملايين الارواح
who look and feel rather like us, when you're up close.
والذي يبدو ويشعر إلي حٍد ما مثلنا، عندما تكون بقربه
I'm sorry to laugh here, but you do look so different
أعتذر لانني أضحك هنا، ولكن حقيقة تبدو مختلفا
than you did in Haight-Ashbury in the '60s.
مما كنت في هايت-اشبيري في الستينات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I want to argue that this is the moment that you are designed for.
ولكني أود اجادل ان هذه هي اللحظة المعدة لذلك.
It is the flowering of the seeds you planted
أنه إلازدهار من البذور التي زرعتموها
in earlier, headier days.
في ايام سابقة، اكثر شِّدة.
Ideas that you gestated in your youth.
أفكار حملتوها في صباكم.
This is what excites me.
هذا ما يثيرني.
This room was born for this moment,
هذه القاعة ولدت لهذه اللحظة،
is really what I want to say to you tonight.
وهي حقيقة ما وددت قوله لكم الليلة.
Most of you started out wanting to change the world, didn't you?
معظمكم بدأو راغبين في تغيير العالم، أليس كذلك؟
Most of you did, the digital world.
معظمكم فعل، العالم الرقمي.
Well, now, actually because of you,
حسنا، ألان، حقيقةً وبفضلكم،
it is possible to change the physical world.
من الممكن تغيير العالم المادي.
It's a fact.
إنها حقيقة.
Economists confirm it, and they know much more than I do.
إلإقتصاديون أكدو ذلك، وهم يعلمون أكثر مما أعلم.
So why, then, are we not pumping our fists into the air?
فلماذا، إذاً، لا نرفع قبضاتنا في الهواء؟
Probably because when we admit we can do something about it,
ربما لأننا عندما نعترف بأننا يمكن أن نفعل شيئا حيال ذلك،
we've got to do something about it.
يجب أن نفعل شيئاً حيال ذلك.
It is a pain in the arse.
إنه ألم في المؤخرة.
This equality business is actually a pain in the arse.
موضوع المساواة في الواقع هو ألم في المؤخرة.
But for the first time in history, we have the technology;
ولكن لأول مرة في التاريخ، نحن نمتلك التكنلوجيا،
we have the know-how; we have the cash;
نحن لدينا من يعلم كيف يطوعها ، لدينا الاموال،
we have the life-saving drugs.
لدينا عقاقير منقذة للحياة.
Do we have the will?
هل لدينا الإرادة؟
I hope this is obvious, but I'm not a hippie.
آمل ان يكون هذا واضح، لانني لست روحانياً.
And I'm not really one for the warm, fuzzy feeling.
و انا لست أحد تلك الاحاسيس، الحارة الغامضة
I do not have flowers in my hair.
وليس لدي زهور علي شعري.
Actually, I come from punk rock.
في الواقع، انا اتيت من فرقة للروك المشاكسين.
The Clash wore big army boots, not sandals.
المشاكسون يرتدون احذية جيش كبيرة، ليس صنادل.
But I know toughness when I see it.
لكني أعرف الصلابة عندما اراها.
And for all the talk of peace and love on the West Coast,
ومع كل الكلام عن السلام والمحبة في الساحل الغربي،
there was muscle to the movement that started out here.
كانت هناك عضلات للحركات التي بدأت بالظهور هنا.
You see, idealism detached from action is just a dream.
كما ترون، المثالية بعيداً عن العمل مجرد حلم.
But idealism allied with pragmatism,
لكن المثالية المتحالفة مع الواقعية،
with rolling up your sleeves and making the world bend a bit,
حيث تشّمر عن ساعديك و تجعل العالم ينحني قليلاً،
is very exciting. It's very real. It's very strong.
إنه مُثير جداً، إنه حقيقي جداً، إنه قوي جداً.
And it's very present in a crowd like you.
ومتوفر بكثرة في حشد من الناس مثلكم.
Last year at DATA, this organization I helped set up,
في العام الماضي في داتا، هذه المنظمة التي ساعدت في إنشائها،
we launched a campaign to summon this spirit
اطلقنا حملة لحشد هذه الروح
in the fight against AIDS and extreme poverty.
في مجال مكافحة الايدز وشدّة الفقر.
We're calling it the ONE Campaign.
نحن نسميها الحملة الاولى.
It's based on our belief that the action of one person
أنها مبنية على إعتقادنا بأن عمل شخص واحد
can change a lot,
يمكن أن يغير الكثير،
but the actions of many coming together as one
لكن اعمال اشخاص عديدون سوياً ككتلة
can change the world.
يمكن أن يغير العالم.
Well, we feel that now is the time to prove we're right.
حسناً ، فإننا نرى أن الوقت قد حان الآن لنثبت أننا علي حق.
There are moments in history when civilization redefines itself.
هناك لحظات في التاريخ عندما تعيد الحضارة تعريف نفسها.
We believe this is one.
نحن نعتقد هذه إحداها.
We believe that this could be the time when the world finally decides
نحن نعتقد بان هذه يمكن ان تكون اللحظة التي يقرر فيها العالم اخيراً
that the wanton loss of life in Africa is just no longer acceptable.
أن الخسائر الفادحة في الانفس في أفريقيا لم يعد مقبولا أكثر.
This could be the time that we finally get serious
هذا يمكن ان يكون الوقت الذي نصبح جادين
about changing the future for most people who live on planet Earth.
حول تغيير المستقبل لمعظم الناس الذين يعيشون علي سطح كوكب الارض.
Momentum has been building.
فقد إزداد الزخم.
Lurching a little, but it's building.
يترنح قليلاً، ولكنه يزداد.
This year is a test for us all,
هذا العام هو إختبار لنا كُلنا،
especially the leaders of the G8 nations,
خاصة قادة دول مجموعة الثمانية ،
who really are on the line here,
الذين هم حقا في خط المواجهة هنا،
with all the world in history watching.
مع كل دول العالم في تاريخ يُراقب.
I have been, of late, disappointed with the Bush Administration.
وكنت، مؤخراً، قد أُصبت بخيبة امل مع إدارة بوش.
They started out with such promise on Africa.
لقد بدأو وعد من هذا القبيل لافريقيا.
They made some really great promises,
لقد وعدو ببعض الوعود العظيمة،
and actually have fulfilled a lot of them.
والواقع انهم أنجزو الكثير منها.
But some of them they haven't.
لكن بعضها لم ينفذ.
They don't feel the push from the ground, is the truth.
أنهم لم يشعروا بالضغط من القواعد، هي الحقيقة.
But my disappointment has much more perspective
لكن خيبة أملي لديها وجهة نظر اكبر بكثير
when I talk to American people,
عندما أتحدث مع الشعب الامريكي،
and I hear their worries about the deficit,
واسمع عن قلقهم بشأن العجز،
and the fiscal well being of their country.
و الرفاهية المادية لبلدهم.
I understand that.
انا أفهم ذلك.
But there's much more push from the ground than you'd think,
لكن هناك المزيد من الضغوط من القواعد اكثر مما تعتقدون،
if we got organized.
إذا بدأنا بالتنظيم.
What I try to communicate, and you can help me if you agree,
ما أحاول توصيله، ويمكنكم مساعدتي اذا وافقتم،
is that aid for Africa is just great value for money
هو أن المساعدات لافريقيا ، كان مجرد قيمة كبيرة للمال
at a time when America really needs it.
في وقت كانت فيه أمريكا تحتاج إليها حقا.
Putting it in the crassest possible terms,
وضعتها في أحرج وضع ممكن،
the investment reaps huge returns.
الاستثمار يجني عوائد ضخمة.
Not only in lives saved, but in goodwill, stability
ليس فقط في إنقاذ الأرواح ، ولكن في حسن النية ، والاستقرار ،
and security that we'll gain.
والامن الذي سوف نكتسبه.
So this is what I hope that you will do, if I could be so bold,
ولذلك فإن هذا هو ما آمل ان تفعلوه ، إذا أمكن أن اكون جريئاً ،
and not have it deducted from my number of wishes.
ومن غير ان تنقص من عدد امنياتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What I hope is that beyond individual merciful acts,
ما أتمناه يتجاوز الأفعال الفردية الرحيمة،
that you will tell the politicians to do right by Africa,
بانك سوف تقول للسياسيين يجب إحقاق الحق لأفريقيا،
by America and by the world.
من جانب أمريكا وجانب العالم.
Give them permission, if you like,
أمنحوهم الإذن، إذا تفضلتم،
to spend their political capital and your financial capital,
ليتصرفوا في عواصمهم السياسية ورؤوس أموالكم،
your national purse on saving the lives of millions of people.
حوافظم الوطنية للأموال في إنقاذ ارواح الملايين من الناس.
That's really what I would like you to do.
هذا حقيقةً ما أودكم ان تعملوه.
Because we also need your intellectual capital:
لاننا ايضاً بحوجة لراس المال الفكري:
your ideas, your skills, your ingenuity.
افكاركم، مهاراتكم، براعاتكم.
And you, at this conference, are in a unique position.
وانتم، في هذا الملتقي، في وضع فريد.
Some of the technologies we've been talking about, you invented them,
بعض التكنولوجيات التي كنا نتحدث عنها، انتم اخترعتموها،
or at least revolutionized the way that they're used.
أو علي الاقل ثورة في الطريقة التي تستخدم.
Together you have changed the zeitgeist from analog to digital,
معاً قمتم بتغيير روح العصر من التماثلي إلى الرقمي،
and pushed the boundaries.
وازحتم الحدود.
And we'd like you to give us that energy.
وانا اريد منكم ان تمنحونا الطاقة.
Give us that kind of dreaming, that kind of doing.
امنحونا ذلك النوع من الحلم، ذلك النوع من العمل..
As I say, there're two things on the line here.
كما قُلت، هنالك امران علي الخط هنا.
There's the continent Africa.
هناك القارة الافريقية.
But there's also our sense of ourselves.
ولكن هناك أيضا إحساسنا بأنفسنا.
People are starting to figure this out.
بدأ الناس باستنتاج ذلك.
Movements are springing up.
الحركات بدات بالظهور.
Artists, politicians, pop stars, priests, CEOs,
فنانين، سياسيين، نجوم غناء، قساوسة، كبار المدراء تنفيذيين،
NGOs, mothers' unions, student unions.
منظمات غير حكومية، إتحادات الامهات، اتحادات طلابية.
A lot of people are getting together, and working
الكثير من الناس يجتمعون سوياً، ويعملون
under this umbrella I told you about earlier, the ONE Campaign.
تحت هذه المظلة التي حدثتكم عنها سابقاً، الحملة الاولى.
I think they just have one idea in their mind,
انا اعتقد ان لديهم فقط فكرة واحدة في عقولهم،
which is, where you live in the world
التي هي، اين تعيش في العالم،
should not determine whether you live in the world.
لايجب ان يحدد ما إذا كنت ستعيش في العالم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
History, like God, is watching what we do.
التاريخ، مثل إلإله، أنه يراقب ما نفعل.
When the history books get written,
عندما تُكتب كتب التاريخ
I think our age will be remembered for three things.
اعتقد ان عصرنا سيُذكر لثلاثة اشياء.
Really, it's just three things this whole age will be remembered for.
حقيقة، انها فقط ثلاثة أشياء سنُذكر بها.
The digital revolution, yes.
الثورة الرقمية، نعم.
The war against terror, yes.
الحرب ضد الارهاب، نعم.
And what we did or did not do to put out the fires in Africa.
وماذا فعلنا او لم نفعل لإخماد النيران في أفريقيا.
Some say we can't afford to. I say we can't afford not to.
البعض يقول ليس بمقدورنا فعل شئ، انا أقول لايمكننا ان نكتفي بذلك.
Thank you, thank you very much.
شكراً لكم، شكراً لكم جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Okay, my three wishes.
حسناً، امنياتي الثلاث.
The ones that TED has offered to grant.
تلك التي عرضت تيد منحه.
You see, if this is true, and I believe it is,
أترون، لو كان هذا صحيح، وانا أعتقد انه كذلك،
that the digital world you all created has uncoupled
ان العالم الرقمي الذي خلقتموه جميعاً قد فصل
the creative imagination from the physical constraints of matter,
المخيلة الخلاقة من القيود المادية لهذه المسألة
this should be a piece of piss.
هذا يجب ان يكون جزء من شخ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I should add that this started out as a much longer list of wishes.
يجب ان اضيف ان ذلك بدأ كمشروع قائمة طويلة من الامنيات.
Most of them impossible, some of them impractical
معظمهم من المستحيلات، بعضهم غير عملي
and one or two of them certainly immoral.
وواحد أو أثنين منهم اكيد غير أخلاقي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This business, it gets to be addictive, you know what I mean,
هذا العمل، يبدو انه إدمان، تعلمون ما أعني،
when somebody else is picking up the tab.
عندما يقوم شخص اخر بالتقاط البقشيش.
Anyway, here's number one.
علي أي حال، ها هنا الأولى.
I wish for you to help build a social movement
اتمني منكم ان تساعدوا في بناء حركة إجتماعية
of more than one million American activists for Africa.
من أكثر من مليون شخص من النشطاء الأمريكيين لأفريقيا.
That is my first wish.
تلك هي أمنيتي الاولة.
I believe it's possible.
انا مؤمن انه جائز.
A few minutes ago, I talked about all the citizens' campaigns that are springing up.
منذ دقائق قليلة، تحدثت عن حملة كل المواطنين التي بدات بالظهور.
You know, there's lots out there.
اتعلمون، هناك الكثير منها.
And with this one campaign as our umbrella,
ومع الحملة إلاولي مثل مظلتنا،
my organization, DATA, and other groups,
منظمتي، داتا، ومجموعات اُخري،
have been tapping into the energy and the enthusiasm
ظلت تتصنت علي الطاقة والاحسان
that's out there from Hollywood into the heartland of America.
التي خرجت من هناك من هوليوود في قلب أميركا.
We know there's more than enough energy to power this movement.
نحن نعلم ان هناك اكثر مما يكفي من الطاقة لتزويد تلك الحركة.
We just need your help in making it happen.
نحن فقط نريد مساعدتكم في تحقيق ذلك.
We want all of you here, church America, corporate America,
نحن نُريدكم جمعياُ هنا، الكنائس الامريكية، المؤسسات الامريكية،
Microsoft America, Apple America, Coke America,
مايكروسوفت الامريكية، آبل الامريكية، كوكا الامريكية،
Pepsi America, nerd America, noisy America.
بيبسي الامريكية، أمريكا المجتهدة، امريكا الصاخبة.
We can't afford to be cool and sit this one out.
نحن لايسعنا ان نتظاهر بالبرود والسكوت عن هذا الامر.
I do believe if we build a movement that's one million Americans strong,
انا حقيقي أؤمن بأنه إذا كونت حركة من مليون أمريكي قوي،
we're not going to be denied.
لن يتم رفضنا .
We will have the ear of Congress.
سنحصل على إنتباه الكونغرس.
We'll be the first page in Condi Rice's briefing book,
سنصبح اول صفحة في صحيفة اعمال كوندي رايس،
and right into the Oval Office.
ومباشرة في عُمق البيت الابيض.
If there's one million Americans -- and I really know this --
إذا كان هناك مليون من الامريكان -- وانا حقيقي أعلم ذلك --
who are ready to make phone calls,
الذين هم على استعداد لإجراء مكالمات هاتفية ،
who are ready to be on email,
الذين هم على استعداد ليكتبوا رسائل البريد الإلكتروني.
I am absolutely sure that we can actually change
أنا مُتأكد تماماً من اننا يمكن حقيقةً ان نُغير
the course of history, literally, for the continent of Africa.
مسار التاريخ، حرفياً، للقارة الافريقية.
Anyway, so I'd like your help in getting that signed up.
علي أي حال، لذا أريد مساعدتكم في الحصول علي ذلك بالتوقيعات .
I know John Gage and Sun Microsystems are already on board for this,
أنا أعلم أن جون كيج و شركة صن مايكروسيستمس بالفعل علي الطليعة في الامر،
but there's lots of you we'd like to talk to.
لكن هناك الكثير منكم نود التحدث إليهم.
Right, my second wish, number two.
الحق، أُمنيتي الثانية، رقم أثنين.
I would like one media hit for every person on the planet
أود وسيلة إعلامية من أجل كل شخص على هذا الكوكب
who is living on less than one dollar a day.
الذي يعيش علي أقل من دولار واحد يومياً.
That's one billion media hits.
هذه بليون وسيلة أعلامية.
Could be on Google, could be on AOL.
يمكن أن تكون علي قوقل، يمكن أن تكون علي امريكان اونلاين.
Steve Case, Larry, Sergey -- they've done a lot already.
ستيف كيس، لاري، سيرجي -- فعلوا الكثير مسبقاً.
It could be NBC. It could be ABC.
يمكن ان تكون ان بي سي، يمكن ان تكون اي بي سي.
Actually we're talking to ABC today about the Oscars.
في الواقع كنا نتحدث اليوم إلي اي بي سي حول جوائز الاوسكار.
We have a film, produced by Jon Kamen at Radical Media.
لدينا فيلم، من انتاج جون كامين في راديكال ميديا.
But you know, we want, we need some airtime for our ideas.
ولكن كما تعلمون ، نحن نريد ، ونحن بحاجة لبعض البث لأفكارنا.
We need to get the math; we need to get the statistics out to the American people.
نحن بحاجة لتوصيل الحسابات، ونحن بحاجة لتوصيل الإحصاءات إلى الشعب الأمريكي.
I really believe that old Truman line,
أعتقد حقا أن خط ترومان القديم ،
that if you give the American people the facts,
إنه إذا أعطيت للشعب الأمريكي الوقائع،
they'll do the right thing.
سوف يفعلون الشيء الصحيح.
And, the other thing that's important is that this is not Sally Struthers.
أيضاً، الشئ الاخر المهم، ان هذا ليس سالي سترثرس.
This has to be described as an adventure, not a burden.
هذه يجب ان يكون وصفها بانها مغامرة ، وليس عبئاً.
(Video): One by one they step forward,
(فيديو): خطوة بخطوة يتقدمون للامام،
a nurse, a teacher, a homemaker,
الممرضة، المعلم، ربات المنازل،
and lives are saved.
ويتم إنقاذ الارواح.
The problem is enormous.
المشكلة هائلة.
Every three seconds one person dies.
في كل ثلاث ثواني يموت شخص.
Another three seconds, one more.
ثلاث ثواني اُخري، شخص اخر.
The situation is so desperate in parts of Africa,
ذلك هو الوضع اليائس في أجزاء من أفريقيا،
Asia, even America,
قارة آسيا، حتي أمريكا
that aid groups, just as they did for the tsunami,
ان جماعات الاغاثة ، تماما كما فعلوا بالنسبة للتسونامي
are uniting as one, acting as one.
يجتمعون في وحدة، ويتصرفون كوحدة.
We can beat extreme poverty, starvation, AIDS.
نحن نستطيع قهر شّدة الفقر، المجاعات، الايدز.
But we need your help.
لكن نريد مساعدتكم.
One more person, letter, voice
إضافة شخص اخر، خطاب، صوت
will mean the difference between life and death
سوف تعني الفرق بين الحياة و الموت
for millions of people.
لملايين الناس.
Please join us by working together.
يرجى الانضمام إلينا عن طريق العمل معاً.
Americans have an unprecedented opportunity.
الشعب الامريكي لديه فرصة لا مثيل لها.
We can make history.
يمكننا نحن صنع التاريخ.
We can start to make poverty history.
نحن نستطيع ان نجعل الفقر تاريخاً.
One, by one, by one.
واحدأ، تلو الاخر، تلو الاخر.
Please visit ONE at this address.
يُرجي زيارة منظمة "الأول" علي هذا العنوان.
We're not asking for your money. We're asking for your voice.
نحن لا نطلب اموالكم، نحن نطلب أصواتكم.
Bono: All right. I wish for TED to truly show the power of information,
بونو : حسنا. أود حقا لتيد أن تظهر قوة المعلومات.
its power to rewrite the rules and transform lives,
أنها قوة لاعادة كتابة قواعد وتحويل الارواح ،
by connecting every hospital, health clinic and school
بربط كل مستشفي، مستوصف ومدرسة
in one African country.
في بلد أفريقي واحد.
And I would like it to be Ethiopia.
وأتمني ان تكون أثيوبيا.
I believe we can connect every school in Ethiopia,
وأعتقد أننا يمكن ربط كل مدرسة في إثيوبيا ،
every health clinic, every hospital --
كل مستوصف صّحي، كل مستشفي.
we can connect to the Internet.
يمكننا الاتصال بالإنترنت.
That is my wish, my third wish.
هذه هي أمنيتي، أمنيتي الثالثة.
I think it's possible.
أعتقد أن ذلك ممكن.
I think we have the money and brains in the room to do that.
أعتقد أن لدينا المال والعقول في هذه الغرفة للقيام بذلك.
And that would be a mind-blowing wish to come true.
وذلك يمكن ان يكون امنية غالية تصبح حقيقة.
I've been to Ethiopia, as I said earlier.
انا كنت في إثيوبيا، كما ذكرت سابقاً.
It's actually where it all started for me.
في واقع الامر حيث بدأ كل شئ بالنسبة إلي.
The idea that the Internet, which changed all of our lives,
الفكرة القائلة بأن الإنترنت ، والذي غيّر حياتنا جميعا ،
can transform a country -- and a continent
يمكن ان يحّول البلد -- و القارة
that has hardly made it to analog, let alone digital -- blows my mind.
الذي بالكاد توصل إلي نظام التناظر ، ناهيك عن الرقمية -- يصيبني بالذهول.
But it didn't start out that way.
لكنه لم يبدأ في هذا الاتجاه.
The first long-distance line from Boston to New York
أول خط مكالمات طويلة من بوسطن إلي نيويورك
was used in 1885 on the phone.
أُستُخدم في العام 1885 في خدمة الهاتف.
It was just nine years later that Addis Ababa
لقد كان فقط بعد تسع أعوام من ذلك أن أديس ابابا
was connected by phone to Harare, which is 500 kilometers away.
كانت متصلة عبر الهاتف الى هراري التي تبعد 500 كيلومترا.
Since then, not that much has changed.
ومنذ ذلك الحين ، لم يحدث تغيير كثير.
The average waiting time to get a landline in Ethiopia
فإن متوسط وقت الانتظار للحصول على خط أرضي في اثيوبيا
is actually about seven or eight years.
في الواقع حوالي سبع إلي ثماني سنوات.
But wireless technology wasn't dreamt up then.
ولكن التكنولوجيا اللاسلكية لم يكن يحلم بها في ذلك الحين.
Anyway, I'm Irish, and as you can see,
علي أي حال، أنا أيرلندي، كما ترون ذلك،
I know how important talking is.
أنا أعرف أهمية التخاطب.
Communication is very important for Ethiopia -- will transform the country.
التواصل مهم جدا بالنسبة لإثيوبيا -- ستحول البلاد.
Nurses getting better training,
الممرضات يحصلون على أفضل تدريب،
pharmacists being able to order supplies,
الصيادلة يمكنهم طلب وسائل الدعم،
doctors sharing their expertise in all aspects of medicine.
الاطباء يمكنهم تقاسم خبراتهم في كل مجالات الطب.
It's a very, very good idea to get them wired.
إنها فكرة جيدة جداً، جداً لربطهم لاسلكياً.
And that is my third and final wish for you at the TED conference.
و هذه هي أمنيتي الثالثة والاخيرة لكم في مؤتمر تيد.
Thank you very much once again.
شكرا جزيلا مرة أخرى
(Applause)
(تصفيق)